Finding Aid for Leslie A. White Papers 1921-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Leslie A. White Papers 1921-1974
White, Leslie A., 1900-1975.
26 linear feet
Professor of anthropology at University of Michigan, student of the culture of the Pueblo Indians of the southwestern United States, and of the career of early American anthropologist, Lewis H. Morgan. Correspondence files, articles and reviews relating to all phases of his anthropological interests, research notes on Lewis H. Morgan, and field notes pertaining to his trips among the Pueblo Indians, and collection of scholarly publications.
86358 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Leslie White (donor no. 4780 ) and his literary executors, and came to the library in several accessions, 1969-1976.
The collection is open for research.
Leslie White was an influential American anthropologist and anthropological theorist who in his writings and teachings espoused the importance of evolutionary theory and helped top revive the work of Lewis Henry Morgan as one of the pioneers of American anthropology.
Leslie A. White was born on January 19, 1900 in Salida, Colorado to Alvin Lincoln White, a Methodist minister, and Mildred May Millard White. His childhood was unstable, with many moves following his parents' divorce in 1905. After high school, White worked as a stenographer and bookkeeper in Louisiana until 1918 when he enlisted in the Navy. Following his discharge the following year, he studied at Louisiana State University. In 1921, he transferred to Columbia University where he received his A.B. in 1923 and his A.M. in psychology in 1924. He continued his education at the University of Chicago receiving his Ph.D. in sociology and anthropology in 1927.
From 1927 to 1930, White taught at the University of Buffalo, then came to the University of Michigan where he remained from 1930 to 1970. He was promoted to full professor in 1943 and served as chairman of the department of anthropology from 1945 to 1957. Following his retirement from the U-M, White was a visiting professor at San Francisco State College and the University of California at Santa Barbara.
White was extremely active as a teacher and researcher in his discipline. He made numerous field trips to the Keresan Pueblos and to the Pueblo of Taos, New Mexico between 1926 and 1957 and was leader of the Ethnological Field Party of the Laboratory of Anthropology, Sante Fe, New Mexico, to the Hopi pueblo of Oraibi in the summer of 1932. In addition, White was the author of many articles, monographs and books. Some of the most important monographs were on the Acoma, San Felipe, Santo Domingo, Santa Ana and Sia Pueblos. The books which best expressed his evolutionary and culturological theory and interpretation were The Science of Culture (1949) and The Evolution of Culture (1959). White was the leading scholar of the life and career of anthropologist Lewis Henry Morgan, editing Morgan's travel journal and his Indian Journals, 1859-1862.
White was visiting professor at a number of universities. Also professional active, he was president of the Central States Anthropological Society, president of the American Anthropological Association (1963-1964), and vice president of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (1958).
The Leslie A. White papers document the fifty-year career of one of America's most distinguished and influential anthropologists. The collection documents through correspondence and other materials the development of modern anthropological theory and practice, particularly the concept of cultural evolution and his theory that the control of energy is basic to the evolution of culture. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Course Work; University Career; Biographical/Personal; Writings; Speeches and Lectures; Miscellaneous; Field Notes and Research Trips; and Published Materials.
Subjects:
American Anthropological Association.; Anthropology.; Nuclear energy.; Goldenweiser, Alexander, 1880-1940.; Humphrey, Norman Daymond.; Indians of North America.; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881.; Pueblo Indians.; Religion.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anthropology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; University of Michigan--Religion.; White, Leslie A., 1900-1975.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Anthropology.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942.; Indians of North America--British Columbia.; Kwakiutl Indians.; San Francisco State College.; Vancouver Island (B.C.); White, Leslie A., 1900-1975.
Contributors:
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; American Association for the Advancement of Science.; American Folklore Society.; Bain, Read, 1892-; Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1889-1968.; Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.; Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1948.; Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-1971.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942.; Childe, V. Gordon (Vere Gordon), 1892-1957.; Cole, Fay-Cooper, b. 1881.; Connable, Alfred B. (Alfred Barnes), 1904-; Hayakawa, S. I. (Samuel Ichiyé), 1906-; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963.; Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1905-1960.; Kroeber, A. L. (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960.; Levi-Strauss, Claude.; Linton, Ralph, 1893-1953.; McLuhan, Marshall, 1911-1980; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990.; Osgood, Cornelius, 1905-1985; Parsons, Elsie Worthington Clews, 1875-1941.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; Sagan, Carl, 1934-1996; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939.; Spier, Leslie, 1893-1961.; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick, 1907-1968.; White, Mary P.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
Subjects:
American Anthropological Association.; Anthropology.; Nuclear energy.; Goldenweiser, Alexander, 1880-1940.; Humphrey, Norman Daymond.; Indians of North America.; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881.; Pueblo Indians.; Religion.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anthropology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; University of Michigan--Religion.; White, Leslie A., 1900-1975.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Anthropology.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942.; Indians of North America--British Columbia.; Kwakiutl Indians.; San Francisco State College.; Vancouver Island (B.C.); White, Leslie A., 1900-1975.
Contributors:
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.; American Association for the Advancement of Science.; American Folklore Society.; Bain, Read, 1892-; Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1889-1968.; Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.; Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1948.; Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-1971.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942.; Childe, V. Gordon (Vere Gordon), 1892-1957.; Cole, Fay-Cooper, b. 1881.; Connable, Alfred B. (Alfred Barnes), 1904-; Hayakawa, S. I. (Samuel Ichiyé), 1906-; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963.; Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1905-1960.; Kroeber, A. L. (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960.; Levi-Strauss, Claude.; Linton, Ralph, 1893-1953.; McLuhan, Marshall, 1911-1980; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.; Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990.; Osgood, Cornelius, 1905-1985; Parsons, Elsie Worthington Clews, 1875-1941.; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.; Sagan, Carl, 1934-1996; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939.; Spier, Leslie, 1893-1961.; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick, 1907-1968.; White, Mary P.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence is the largest and most important series within the collection providing documentation of White's entire career, his teaching and research, his interaction with colleagues and other notable anthropologists, and his mentoring of students and young anthropologists. The files, with some slight exceptions are in the order maintained by White. The earliest correspondence (1921 to 1944) is arranged chronologically by day. Correspondence thereafter is arranged by academic year and then alphabetically. With some individuals, White maintained separate named files. Notable among these correspondents were Harry Elmer Barnes, H. L. Mencken, Robert Carneiro, Edward Norbeck, and Elsie Clews Parsons. It should be noted that these were by no means the only individuals that White corresponded with on a regular basis. The dated files include significant exchanges with many anthropologists and academicians. Appended to this finding aid is a selected list of Leslie White's correspondents.
  - By date
    - Undated 1921-1944, 9 folders (Box 1)
      (in chronological order by day)
    - 1943/44 [A-Z]-, 1946 [A-Z], 21 folders (Box 1)
      (arranged alphabetically beginning in 1943/44)
    - 1947 [A-Z]-, 1949 [A-Q], 31 folders (Box 2)
    - 1949 [R-Z]-, 1951/52 [A-K], 44 folders (Box 3)
    - 1951/52 [L-Z]-, 1955/56 [A-M], 47 folders (Box 4)
    - 1955/55 [N-Z]-, 1959/60 [A-H], 51 folders (Box 5)
    - 1959/60 [I-Z]-, 1961/62 [A-Z], 44 folders (Box 6)
    - 1962/63 [A-Z]-, 1965/66 [A-F], 47 folders (Box 7)
    - 1965/66 [G-Z]-, 1968/69 [A-Z], 44 folders (Box 8)
    - 1970-1975 [A-Z], 32 folders (Box 9)
    - Unidentified correspondence 1970-1975 (Box 9)
  - By correspondent
    - American Anthropological Association
      - With Stephen T. Boggs, executive secretary 1961-1964 (Box 10)
      - General 1959-1964 (Box 10)
        LAW was president in 1964
      - Visiting Lecturers Program 1959-1960 (Box 10)
    - Harry Elmer Barnes 1913-1968, 14 folders (Box 10)
    - Robert L. Carneiro 1950-1974, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Darwin Centennial Celebration 1959 (Box 10)
    - Farrar, Straus & Giroux 1968-1969 (Box 10)
    - Genia Gonzales 1969-1974, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - James Hamilton 1965-1966 (Box 10)
    - H. L. Mencken 1943-1948 (Box 10)
    - Edward Norbeck 1951-1975, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Elsie Clews Parsons 1926-1941 (Box 10)
      (concerns Pueblo Indian research)
    - Pueblo Indian correspondents 1941-1949, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Course work: Columbia University/University of Chicago 1923-1926
  The Course work series consists of papers, examinations, and other materials accumulated by Leslie White while a student at Columbia University and the University of Chicago. White was a student of R. S. Woodworth at Columbia and of Fay-Cooper Cole at the University of Chicago. He also was part of a summer course at UCLA taught by Frank Thilly. Out of this class, White put together his own thoughts on matters of right and wrong and expounded his own view of ethics.
  - Papers written at the University of Chicago (Box 11)
  - Papers concerning courses at Columbia University and the University of Chicago 1923-1925 (Box 11)
  - Papers written for Professor Woodworth's courses in psychology at Columbia University 1923-1924 (Box 11)
  - Student papers written while at Columbia and University of Chicago (Box 11)
  - Papers written at the University of Chicago 1924-1925, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Masters Thesis written under R.S. Woodworth at Columbia University 1923-1924 (Box 11)
  - Papers and Reviews written at Columbia University and the University of Chicago 1924-1926 (Box 11)
  - Notes and examinations from classes of Fay-Cooper Cole at the University of Chicago (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous papers and Ph.D. exams of White (Box 11)
  - "700 Pages of Worthwhile Reading" by R.S. Woodworth at Columbia University 1924 (Box 11)
  - Notes on course taught by Frank Thilly of Cornell at UCLA, Summer 1923 (Box 11)
    (regarding LAW's view of ethics)
- University career
  The University career series pertains mainly to White's four decade career at the University of Michigan. A small portion is from the 1920s when he taught at the University of Buffalo. The University of Michigan portion of this series detail White's influence as a teacher as seen in student evaluations of his classes and the notes made by two of his students from 1933 and 1953 which were incorporated into the collection.
  Part of the University career series concerns White's administrative responsibilities as department chairman and the impact of his iconoclastic views. There were at least two instances when White's treatment of religion within his classes led to criticism within the religious community and attempts to have him disciplined.
  - University of Buffalo
    - Course Outline and memorandum circa 1927 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan Extension Service
    - Comments by Detroit Students on White's "Evolution of Culture" course 1937-1938 (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan course materials
    - Student evaluations
      - Anthropology 191 (Box 11)
      - Anthropology 157, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Anthropology 452 (Box 11)
      - Anthropology 152, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Anthropology 691 (Box 11)
      - Anthropology 791 (Box 11)
    - Notes of students on White classes
      - Notes of Marvin K. Opler on Anthropology 32 1933 (Box 11)
      - Notes of Arthur Markendorf on Anthropology 191, Fall 1953 (Box 11)
    - Course readings, etc. (Box 11)
  - University of Michigan administrative papers
    - Minutes of the Department of Anthropology 1944-1948 (Box 11)
    - Dept. of Anthropology promotion miscellanea (Box 11)
    - Papers concerning the Museum of Anthropology of the University of Michigan 1941-1944 (Box 11)
    - Distinguished Faculty Achievement Awards Committee 1964-1965 (Box 11)
    - Student notes from lectures in "Mind of Primitive Man," 1943-1944 (Box 11)
      (Used in attempt by religious leaders to have White fired)
    - Father McPhillips Episode 1946, 1969 (Box 11)
      (White's treatment of religion in anthropology class and subsequent criticism)
    - Papers concerning the appearance of Claude Levi-Strauss at the University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Celebration 1966 (Box 11)
  - Research proposals; visiting lectureships
    - Guggenheim Foundation proposal for study of cultural evolution 1942 (Box 11)
    - National Science Foundation proposal for study of Capitalist-Democratic Culture and Communist culture 1963 (Box 11)
    - Applications for research funds (Box 11)
    - Correspondence concerning research funds 1952-1968 (Box 11)
    - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences 1959-1961 (Box 11)
- Biographical/Personal
  Biographical and family information about White has been placed in the Biographical/Personal series. Include here are a few photographs of White, clippings from throughout his career, correspondence with family members, and diaries and expense books. The diaries are detailed and insightful. Unfortunately diaries for key periods in White's life are missing, and one of the diaries has obviously had pages excised.
  - Biographical information (Box 11)
  - American Anthropologist obituary of LAW (papers concerning), 1976-1977 (Box 11)
  - Essay by Don Marshall entitled "Leslie A. White: Cultural Evolutionist" (Box 11)
  - Photographs (Box 11)
    Copy print photographs (made 1960s) of Kwakuitl Indians of Vancouver Island, British Columbia which White used in a 1960s publication on the field work (1890s) of Franz Boas; portrait of White (1938) and informal photographs of White with students in a classroom at San Francisco State College.
  - Newspaper clippings, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Distinguished Faculty Service Award 1957 (Box 12)
  - White's Seventieth Birthday celebration 1970 (Box 12)
  - Family Correspondence 1970-1975 (Box 12)
  - Letters from Father, A.L. White 1919-1934 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence concerning Herbert White Smith 1967-1969 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence concerning Leslie A. White Papers (Box 12)
  - Letter between dogs, Tobey and Shep (Explanation attached) 1957 (Box 12)
  - Genealogical material (Box 12)
  - Reminiscence of Kansas childhood 1952 (Box 12)
  - Maps drawn by White while employed by his father (Box 12)
  - Inscriptions and marginal notes in books in the Leslie A. White Library (Box 12)
  - Medical Reports (Box 12)
    (includes some personal biographical information)
  - Personal miscellanea; include awards and citations (Box 12)
  - Income Tax 1963-1974, 10 folders (Box 12)
  - Royalties 1961-1963 (Box 12)
  - Insurance Papers (Box 12)
  - Stock Reports (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Papers (Box 12)
  - Visit to Lane, Kansas September 1938 (Box 12)
  - Trip to Mexico 1944 (Box 12)
  - Trip to Russia 1964 (Box 12)
  - Travel Notes 1974, undated (Box 12)
  - Costa Rica, Notes on bull fighting 1972 (Box 12)
  - Diaries 1937-1974 (scattered dates) (Box 12)
  - Personal expense books 1919-1920s (scattered dates) (Box 12)
  - Address books, memorandum books, etc. (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous personal (Box 12)
- Writings and related materials
  White was a prolific writer and copies (including drafts and reprints) are included in the collection. A detailed bibliography of his books and articles is appended to this finding aid. The Writings series includes many of White's unpublished writings, drafts of writings to which White often appended brief notes written at the time the materials came to the library, and early drafts of published materials. Copies of most of White's books and articles will be found in the Published Materials series. In addition, this series includes reviews of White's writing, White's reviews of works by other anthropologists, and correspondence exchange with publishers about his various books and other writings. A bibliography of White's writings is appended to this finding aid.
  - Bibliography 1968 of White' s writings (Box 13)
  - Bibliographical material, includes list of White's reviews and books on Lewis H. Morgan (Box 13)
  - Unpublished writings
    - "Reminiscences of a Navajo Schoolboy" 1928 (Box 13)
    - "Disintegration of Pueblo Culture" 1937 (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - "Gulliver's Voyage to Dementia" 1938 (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - "Planning the Post War World" June 1942 (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - "Words and their Meanings" January 1944 (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - "Cultural Anthropology and Science" 1954 (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - "The Evolution of Culture" 1960 (unpublished) (Box 13)
      (based on lecture at Penn. State University)
    - "One World or None" January 1969 (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - "Biologic versus Sociologic Diagnoses of Ills of Mankind" (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - "The Role of Giant Corporations in American Society" (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - "The Russian Revolution" (unpublished) (Box 13)
    - Unpublished articles: "Why Anti-Semitism Grows Stronger", "The Merging of Nations", and "An Anthropological Perspective" (Box 13)
    - Poetry (Box 13)
  - Drafts
    (includes occasional notes by LAW about article)
    - "The Social Theory of Ethnological Theory" (Box 13)
    - "Definitions and Conceptions of Culture" (Box 13)
    - "The Evolution and Transformation of the Capitalist-Democratic System" 1954 (draft) (Box 13)
    - "Social Organization of Tenure and Control of Wealth" (Box 13)
    - "War: The Big Question Mark" 1955 (draft) (Box 13)
    - "The State and Class Structure" 1954 (draft), 2 folders (Box 13)
    - "Contemporary Encyclopedist" (Harry Elmer Barnes) (Box 13)
    - "Evolutionism and Anti-Evolutionism in American Ethnological Theory" (draft) (Box 13)
    - Preface to new edition 1969 of The Science of Culture (Box 13)
    - Editor's Introduction to Lewis H. Morgan's Ancient Society (Box 13)
    - Definitions prepared for the Dictionary of Social Science, 1957 (Box 13)
    - "Cultural Evolution and the American School of Historical Ethnology" 1932 (draft) (Box 13)
    - "Anti-Evolutionism in Cultural Anthropology" 1940 (draft) (Box 13)
    - "The First Forms of Human Social Organization" (Box 13)
    - "Schools" (Box 13)
    - "Culturology" Drafts (Box 13)
    - Foreword to Acoma Indians (Box 13)
    - "The Adventure of Sociology" (Box 13)
    - "The Adventure of Anthropology" (Box 13)
    - Papers concerning White's paper on Franz Boas 1962-1963 (Box 13)
    - Letters concerning White's "The Ethnography of Franz Boas" 1963 (Box 13)
    - Papers concerning Keregan Indian Colors 1942-1943 (Box 13)
    - Notes for "Man's Place in Nature" (Box 13)
    - Modern Capitalist Culture
      - "The United States from Colonial Times to World War I" (draft for Modern Capitalist Culture) (Box 14)
      - "The State Church in Modern Society" (draft for Modern Capitalist Culture) (Box 14)
      - "The State Church in Capitalist Society" (draft for Modern Capitalist Culture) (Box 14)
      - "Subsidies" (draft for Modern Capitalist Culture) (Box 14)
      - "Social Organization of Tenure and Control" (draft for Modern Capitalist Culture (Box 14)
      - "The Social Consequences of the Fuel Revolution" 1957 (draft for Modern Capitalist Culture) (Box 14)
      - "The Nature of Capitalist-Democratic Culture" (draft for Modern Capitalist Culture) (Box 14)
      - "Introduction to Modern Capitalist Culture" (Box 14)
      - Modern Capitalist Culture (draft), 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Manuscripts of Printed articles and reviews (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Published Articles (Box 14)
  - Articles (published and unpublished), 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Drafts and galleys of published books and articles (Box 15)
  - Reviews of his books/by LAW of books by others
    - Notebook containing book reviews (Box 16)
    - Reviews and notices of The Science of Culture (Box 16)
    - Review of The Science of Culture by The Weekly People, 1958 (Box 16)
    - Reviews and correspondence relating to The Science of Culture, 1958 (Box 16)
    - Reviews of White's The Morgan Journals, 1960 (Box 16)
    - Review of "An Anthropological Appraisal of the Russian Revolution" by Maxim Gorgy in Pravda, 1930 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence and newspaper clippings re "An Anthropological Appraisal of the Russian Revolution," 1930-1931, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Reviews of The Evolution of Culture, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
    - Reviews of books relating to Lewis Henry Morgan (Box 16)
    - Review by White of Technology and Economic Development, 1965 (Box 16)
    - Book reviews by White about his books (Box 16)
    - Reviews by White on anthropological books and topics, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Reviews of books (Box 16)
  - Publisher's correspondence and related
    - Correspondence concerning publication of The Concept of Culture, 1974-1976 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence with McGraw-Hill Book Co. concerning The Evolution of Culture, 1955-1960, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence including permission to quote 1958 (Box 16)
    - Letters responding to gift of White's The Social Organization of Ethnological Theory, 1967 (Box 16)
    - Rejection slips 1939-1949 (Box 16)
- Speeches, lectures, etc.
  The Speeches and lectures series contains copies of the various speeches White gave including press coverage and subsequent correspondence. A talk before the Philosophy Club at the University of Buffalo in 1930 provides a concise statement of some of White's view of religion. Another concerns his views of atomic energy. A videotape of a lecture he gave at the University of Colorado is included in the series.
  - Talk on religion before the Philosophy Club, University of Buffalo March 5, 1930 (Box 16)
  - Principles of his philosophy May 1944 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence concerning "Satellites and Gods" speech 1957-1958 (Box 16)
  - News clippings concerning "Satellites and Gods" speech 1957-1958 (Box 16)
  - "Man, Culture and Human Beings": Address to The American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 16)
  - Papers concerning "Man, Culture and Human Beings?" 1958-1959 (Box 16)
  - Lectures in summer institute in Anthropology-University of Colorado, Boulder 1961 (Box 16)
  - "Culturology"-Outline of lectures 1970-1971 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous addresses (Box 16)
  - Typescripts and printed copies 1953 of lectures on U.M. Telecourse (Box 16)
  - Text of speech, "Atomic energy: An Anthropological Appraisal" read before The American Anthropological Association 1945 (Box 16)